Welcome to the TRT and Hormone
Optimization YouTube channel. And as the
new guest today, we have Dr. Sean.
Welcome to the channel.
>> Thanks for having me. I appreciate you
uh having me here.
>> It's our pleasure. Always nice to see
new doctors coming involved. So, uh
maybe start with introducing yourself uh
to the viewers.
>> Yeah, so I I'm Dr. Sean Sadiki. I'm
board certified in family medicine. Um
but you know pretty much right out of
residency I started training in
functional medicine and really
incorporated HRT and TRT into my
practice uh along with peptide. So uh I
I would say I I take a very try to take
a very holistic approach to hormone
replacement and TRT.
>> And why did you come so interested in
hormone and testosterone replacement?
>> Oh man, that's such a good question. And
uh you know I think the the big one is
that it's such a um underlooked problem.
You know you go to your primary care
doctor um over here and that the
standard panel is like a CBC, CMP,
thyroid, lipid. So you're not even
really looking for testosterone
generally, right? So very
underdiagnosed. Um and then when I was
in residency, I worked at a university
clinic. I was seeing a lot of students a
ton of anxiety and depression. We're
never checking hormones, right? like
we're handing out anti-dopressants,
but maybe the problem is the low
testosterone, right? Which will impact
your mental health. So, I found that we
just weren't looking. It was a problem
that wasn't being addressed, and you
know, you get somebody on testosterone,
you're putting on muscle, you're
decreasing body fat, you're improving
mental health, we've just saved you from
three different medications potentially,
right? So there's this it's cheap, it's
effective, it's available. Um, and it's
it's something the body makes. So
there's so much positive elements to TRT
and HRT. And I felt like this is
something I want to make available to my
patients. I want as many tools in my
toolbox as possible so that I can give
patients the best care that I possibly
can.
>> Yeah. Awesome. That's something I see in
my personal practice as well. I see a
lot of young patients, some 30, 40 year
old guys coming in, they're on
anti-depressants, SSRIs, and um instead
of checking the hormones, they're just
giving all out Yeah. chemicals that uh
just suppress your brain really, instead
of um attacking the root cause of the
problem.
>> Um you told me you are more into a
holistic approach uh to HRT as well.
What does that mean exactly? Yeah. I
mean, so I like to look into why is your
testosterone low? Now, this is a very
difficult question. There's so many
things at play here. So, head trauma,
gut health, um stress levels, heavy
metal exposure, viral exposures,
inflammation levels, uh sleep, right?
So, it's I like to try to take that
approach, but I want to meet the patient
where they are because it takes a lot of
uh patience, discipline, um trial and
error to try to figure out why is your
testosterone low. Not everybody has that
time or that patience to try to figure
it out. So, I would like to do that, but
it's also expensive, right? Like, we're
getting into heavy metal testing. Um
we're getting into more extensive
functional medicine tests, gut health
tests, maybe neurotransmitter testing.
um even hormone metabolism testing. So
that can all add up very quickly.
Whereas you know just a a quick
testosterone free total estrogen and you
know your LHFSH that's it's not cheap
but it's not it's not unreasonable. So I
do like to try to take that approach. I
would love to identify what the cause is
for the person that's leading to their
low testosterone. Um but you know it's
often very difficult to find. So that's
kind of uh what I like to do, but it's
not feasible for everybody.
>> Yeah, we've learned on the channel from
other doctors throughout the years. Uh
we're always talking about primary or
secondary hypogonatism. Um but you just
said there's much more to it, much more
different causes.
Yeah. Um like I I really love to start
with gut health. Um, so gut health is
going to impact your hormones in in many
different ways. So the microbiome can
impact how you're recycling your
testosterone. So whether you're um
excreting your testosterone or you're
pulling it back in to um use it again,
right? So that can impact your
testosterone levels. Your gut microbiome
is going to impact that. Um and then we
can get into leaky gut syndrome where
your gut barrier is not as strong as
we'd like. There's gaps in the barrier.
things are getting through the barrier
that we don't want. Your body may start
to attack those that creates
inflammation that can increase your
cortisol levels. Increases in cortisol
will lead to decreases in testosterone
and then increases in cortisol can also
further increase gut inflammation. So it
becomes this cycle of worsening
inflammation, worsening of your
hormones. Uh some people can even have
lowgrade endotoxin exposure through
their um gut bacteria where the
endotoxin is going into the blood. It's
damaging their testicles, but it's very
lowrade. It's not sepsis. It's you you
wouldn't even feel it. You'd be
asymptomatic, but it is cause causing
organ damage. Um so I'm I'm a really
really big fan of trying to start with
the gut, heal the gut lining, and see if
we can improve testosterone levels that
way. At the very least, I find people's
uh mood improves, their sleep improves,
immune function improves, um if they're
not bloated as much, they tend to feel
better. So, um a lot of benefits to
approaching the gut health.
>> And what kind of investigations do you
start with?
>> Yeah. So, I mean, I like to just start
with a CBC. Even just looking at
monocytes, xenophils, and basopils can
tell us uh you know, there's gut health
patterns, functional patterns we can
look at. Um, and then really if you're
looking at somebody's lifestyle, if
they're not sleeping enough, they're
stressed out, they're drinking alcohol
on a regular basis, they're eating
processed food, uh, seed oils, gluten is
a problem for a lot of people. Um, so
even just taking a good history can tell
me you pro you likely have gut
inflammation. So between the CBC and the
history, we can tell. But then you can
get into stool testing where they're
looking at zulin. um they're looking at
what bacteria do you have any pathic
bacteria do you have any parasites so
you can go much deeper even blood
testing for like anti-gladin you know
you're looking for Crohn's um so the
investigation can can be very deep but
you can also keep it uh pretty simple
and just uh I would say treat for gut
health which is thing nothing that's
overly aggressive you know um colostrum
is great glutamine is great these are
things you could take even if you
weren't sure if you had gut
inflammation, you'd still probably have
some benefit from them and there's very
little risk of something bad happening.
>> Mhm. So, are there men with low
testosterone symptoms and levels that
you can help completely get back to
normal levels um with these uh measures
without giving them testosterone?
>> I would say yes. Yes, you can. I have
seen it happen. Um,
a lot of men don't give me the chance uh
to do so. Like, you know, the the
problem I find
with men in general is that they're not
coming to you until the problem's really
bad, right? And then they they want a
solution as soon as possible. So, there
have I have had cases where I've been
able to improve the gut health and we've
been able to improve the testosterone,
but honestly, I don't get a ton of
chances. Usually I'm doing both at the
same time. Uh so I can't say I'm
consistently getting to see those
results in action.
>> Yeah. And um do you give out next to the
supplements also um special diets to
heal for example leaky gut?
>> Yeah. Um I'm I'm a big fan of the Paleo
diet. Um it's a very low inflammation,
high nutrient-dense diet. Um bone broth
is great for gut health. So, I I like to
think of it as a balance between two
things. You need to decrease what's
going to make your gut health worse, and
you need to increase what's going to
make it better. What I do also find is
if you're like 50/50, it's going to be
on the worst side. Like, you need to
significantly do more of the good and
less of the bad. I would say like 7030,
8020 for most people. Um, so that I've
kind of um that's my starting point for
people is to start with paleo. Now, some
people you you may need to do like a
food sensitivity test or like a DNA test
to see what foods you process um best,
what is best for you, what nutrients do
you need to focus more on. Like for me,
for example, um I did a DNA test that
told me um I'm going to be at high risk
for low vitamin C, low B12, and low
antioxidants. So now those are essential
parts of my supplement routine. Um,
a lot of people are the type where
they'll take 10 15 supplements in a day.
I'm not honestly like I I'll probably
consistently take like five things. So,
I have my core supplements that I'm
always going to take and then I'll take
things um for what I feel like I need in
that moment. Uh, you know, my focus
isn't as good. Okay, I'll take
supplements for that. Oh, my energy is
not as good. I'll take supplements for
that.
um maybe sleep's not as good or I feel a
little stressed. You know, I I'll kind
of rotate other supplements, but I have
my core supplements that are focused on,
you know, my DNA. And often for me,
definitely gut health. I have done a gut
test on myself. I did have um glyadin
um or anti-glyin in my test that came
up. Um and I know guts been a major
issue for me. That's probably part of
the reason I got I get so into this and
I get uh passionate about it. Um I
recently did a treatment on myself with
some peptides. I find I'm sleeping
better. I'm more energized. I'm more
relaxed. Um it's uh you know the gut has
connections to the brain um to the
heart. It's impacting our immune system.
Our neurotransmitters are made in the
gut and sent up to our brain. So, if the
gut is inflamed and that connection
isn't optimal, it's going to impact you
in many, many different ways, even if
it's not just your testosterone.
>> Mhm. Before we get into the peptides and
TRT, um, talking of supplements, uh,
what supplements and what doses maybe do
you recommend every man takes? Um, yeah,
to heal his gut.
>> Um, so glut I like glutamine. I'll do
five grams of glutamine a day. Um, I'll
mix that with um I like to take a
magnesium powder. Um, that the one I'm
not honestly not sure of the dose of
that one, but I mix that I mix those two
together. Um, BPC 157 is great. Um,
laurazzide is great. That's another one
I like to use. Um, BPC at about
somewhere between like 300 and 500
micrograms a day is pretty good. I
believe the laorazzide is 500
micrograms. Don't quote me on that. I'm
not 100% sure of that one. Um I like
colostrum. So there's a lot of great
colostrum brands. Um Armra is pretty
good. You can take a scoop of that, put
it in. I like to mix it all together. I
So what my morning tonic you could call
it is electrolytes, colos uh colostrum,
glutamine,
um and the magnesium powder. I just mix
those all together and that's my um it's
like 750 ml and I kind of drink that
throughout like the first two three
hours of my day. [snorts]
>> Awesome. So if men are impatient or you
cannot help their gut enough um when do
you start TRT actually?
>> Um I mean I have a pretty low threshold.
Um, if if they're symptomatic, then I'm,
you know, as long as their testosterone
is not like really high and they're
symptomatic, okay, then I would pause
and evaluate like, well, it's probably
not your testosterone that's making you
feel this way. Let's optimize everything
else and then we'll re-evaluate. Uh but
you know if patients are symptomatic
like you know uh increased abdominal
fat, trouble putting on muscle, poor
stamina, poor recovery, uh brain fog,
anxiety, depression, erectile
dysfunction, um decreased sex drive, if
they have a combination of any, you
know, you don't have to have all of
them, but if you have a combination of
them, your labs are showing your
suboptimal, I mean, I'm def I'm open to
starting on TRT.
>> Yeah, sure. And what are the most common
um administration routes? Um you get
patients um yeah on injections on cream.
Uh I guess
>> yeah um I would say for me most common
is injection. I mean creams are great.
Um I I have inconsistent results with
creams. I would say sometimes I know
some guys they they respond really
really well. Some people don't. And then
I always worry about the the cream
fatigue like the buildup on. Uh, so I
just kind of chat with patients about
that and let them know that you need to
rotate. Uh, you can't just put it in the
same spot all the time. U, but
injections I would say get the most
consistent results. We can alter um the
dosing very easily. You know, with cream
is a little more difficult. When you're
doing clicks, um, you're getting like
certain amounts with, you know, we can
alter to the 0.1 ml, right? 0.01 ml of
testosterone. So, there's a lot of
flexibility. So, I do like that. Um, and
then there's a compounding pharmacy.
I've been working with that does a
sublingual testosterone. Uh so patients
have been enjoying that one as well, but
I would say my go-to is definitely
injectable.
>> Yeah. Right. Um a question I've asked
many other providers before, but I'll
ask you as well. Um what typical dose do
you start with? Do you start very low
and increase gradually or do you start
high and uh decrease uh after?
[laughter]
>> Well, I like to start low. Um, you know,
I I will base my dosing based on how bad
the symptoms are and how low the
testosterone is, but I would say a a a
low starting point for me is 0.15 ml or
30 milligrams three times a week. Um,
not everybody will start that low, but I
honestly I find a lot of patients
respond really well to that dose. Um,
and then if they need to go higher, that
like that's fine. We keep a close eye on
it. I like to recheck um at least every
three months in the beginning while
we're kind of a tailoring the dose then
but I also tell patients you've at 6
weeks you're not feeling any better then
I don't anticipate you're going to feel
better by 3 months. So then we'll we'll
increase the dose at that point. Um so
0.15 0.2 ml or uh sorry uh let's say 30
milligrams or 40 milligrams three times
a week is like a a dose I like to start
at
>> and then take it up from there. Yeah. I
guess next to TRT, you also recommend
people uh start working out, healthy
diet like you mentioned.
>> Of course. Yeah. So, usually the first
half of my consult is we're just
chatting about lifestyle. And I tell
everybody there's three things that need
to be in order or I can give you all the
stuff in the world. You're never going
to feel your best. You're not going to
feel the way you want to feel. And
that's going to be sleep, diet, and
exercise. I rank sleep as number one.
Diet and exercise are 2A and 2B. I would
say those two are tied. But, you know,
if you're not getting enough sleep,
right off the bat, you're having low
testosterone, right? I think there was a
study that showed um just from not
sleeping enough, there's a an initial
40% decrease in your testosterone. So,
so that's a big one. You know, that's a
for a lot of people,
it's lowhanging fruit, but unfortunately
with hustle culture, it's not always
easy to prioritize sleep. So, you know,
if the guy if the guy can't get the
sleep and we can't get their levels up
naturally, then yeah, TRT is going to be
helpful um in getting them to at least
feel better in the meantime. And I
always tell people like either you're
going to make health a priority or your
pri your health is going to be made a
priority for you. And you don't want you
don't want that. You know, when um part
of why I'm so passionate about this is
when I was in residency, I'm in the
hospital. I'm on the south side of
Chicago. I'm seeing patients on
dialysis, patients with amputated feet,
um skin ulcerations, like just the
quality of life was just terrible, you
know, terrible. They can't travel. Um
they can't eat the things they want to
eat without their blood sugar spiking or
their blood blood pressure going up. So,
we really want to get ahead of that. You
know, we want to avoid that as much as
humanly possible. And in my opinion,
these are very avoidable problems. Um,
>> these are like blood pressure. Diabetes
for most people is a lifestyle problem
>> and it's not easy once you have a I
don't want to just say like oh just stop
eating sugar like it's not that easy. It
is a very addictive substance. Um, and
what if you're maybe your testosterone
is low, you're depressed, your happiness
comes from consuming sugar. We know it
gives you a dopamine spike. So, it's
going to be this, you know, this cycle
that's very tough to break if you're not
working with a functional doctor who's
give who's focusing on getting you the
right nutrients. Let's help with your
sugar cravings. Let's speed up the
weight loss. Let's get your hormones up.
Let's get you motivated. Let's get you
feeling good. Let's get you a a workout
plan that you can stick with. Um, so to
treat those people, in my opinion, you
need a very well-rounded holistic
approach. Throwing diabetes medication
at them is just a temporary solution. I
found all my my my toolbox was what
medication can I add next? You know that
that's all I knew how to do and uh I was
not happy with that. I thought that was
crazy. And the the human species has
been around for so many years. You were
telling me my only solution is a
pharmaceutical. That's all I have to
offer. We learn nothing about lifestyle
in medical school. Nothing about
nutrition. It's and these are the
foundations of health which is which is
crazy. So, you know, it is what it is.
Um, it's an industry, right? Um,
>> and
shareholders
are the priority. These are hospital
systems. These are pharmaceutical
companies. Shareholders are going to be
put before patients. So, in that system,
it's just impossible to put patients
first. You know, they these companies
have a responsibility to put their
shareholders first. Legally, they have
to put their shareholders first, and
they're supposed to be taking care of
patients. So
>> same here in Europe, especially in
Belgium, uh same thing goes on. Um yeah,
at the university, uh conferences, uh
and so on and so on, it's always disease
uh pharmaceutical product, always
disease pill, disease pill. Uh nobody
talks about diet, resistance, training,
lifestyle, sleep. We learn nothing about
that. We don't learn anything about HRT
as well during our medical um education.
>> Nothing. I always tell people if I could
roll up all the benefits of exercise
into a pill, I'd be a trillionaire.
There's nothing out there that is as
good for you as exercise. It treats
everything.
>> Um it improves your sleep, it improves
depression, improves blood pressure,
improves blood sugar. Um obviously
you're going to look better. You're
going to feel better if you you know you
look good, you feel good, right? So, um,
and that's just that's like a very
superficial tip of the iceberg of the
benefits of testosterone. I mean, sorry,
of of, uh, resistance training and
working out, right? Like we could have a
whole podcast just talking about the
benefits or a whole series, I'm sure,
not even just one podcast.
>> Here, even in mainstream media, uh,
fitness for youngsters is demonized.
like testosterone is demonized,
supplements, creatine is demonized. Uh
going to the fitness and wanting to look
good, it's all demonized. It's all
bodybuilding, anabolics, it's all thrown
on the same heap. It's uh yeah, it's
it's incredible. It's nothing about
health. It's all about Yeah.
pharmaceutical agents. You you just wait
till you get sick and then we'll treat
you.
>> Right. Right. Um, you know, like I when
I was in uh residency, we'd be like,
"Oh, you're pre-diabetic. You know,
maybe we'll get you some metformin." Now
I'm like, "You're pre-diabetic, man. We
got to like turn the ship around like
right now or this is going to get
worse." Um, but it's very, you know, I I
don't want my goal isn't to throw
anybody under the bus, right? Because
the problem is when you get 15 or 20
minutes with a patient and they're on a
bunch of medications, you need to make
sure they're safe. You need to evaluate
for new disease processes. you need to
check that, you know, what interactions
are they having with their medication.
You don't even really have time to talk
to these patients about lifestyle. So, I
think the system is unfortunately more
to blame than uh I mean, yeah, medical
education is a problem, but who's making
our medical education, right? Um, so
I I don't think it's I I don't think
it's the doctor's fault. I think it's a
very systemic problem. uh lack of
education, lack of prioritizing um
prevention,
you know, it's unfortunate.
>> You were talking about sleep. Um how do
you help patients manage their sleep
better? Uh any supplements or peptides?
>> Oh man, sleep is honestly a very very
tough one. Um for some people it's very
easy. You know, all people are like,
"Oh, I started taking magnesium. Now I'm
sleeping way better." Right. Uh I would
say magnesium I get great response on in
general. Um but for often people it's
it's how do they turn off their brain,
right? Like how do they stop stressing?
How do they relax? I think if we can
find that problem, then the sleep will
take care of itself. Uh for some people
it's low blood sugar in the middle of
the night. So um they're waking up
because their blood sugar crashes, they
get a cortisol spike to get their blood
sugar back up and then they have trouble
going back to sleep. So for those
people, you can do it. You can
investigate by getting yourself a blood
glucose monitor, which is the expensive
way of doing it. Uh the other way is to
just have something with a little bit of
fat, protein, and carbs right before you
go to bed. If you don't wake up, we know
it was a blood sugar problem. So that
one's a easy thing to look into. Um so I
like uh DIP is an a very interesting
peptide. What it does is it decreases uh
the uh inflammation in sleep centers of
the brain. So, it's not going to put you
to sleep that night, but it will over
time supposed to help you with improving
your sleep. Um, growth hormone peptides
are great. Growth hormone can help with
sleep. So, that'll increase sleep
quality. I can't say. So, what I find is
people report to me they sleep better.
It's not actually helping them uh with
falling asleep if that's the problem for
them. But maybe for people who have
trouble staying asleep, it works pretty
great. Um, but then sleep hygiene is
super important, right? Like so what I
do in my home is I turn off all the
lights. Um my wife and I have set up a
red light strip into our uh like TV
console in our living room where we hang
out. We don't have a TV in our bedroom.
The bedroom is not used for anything
other than sleep and you know whatever
else we do in the bedroom. Um but that's
it. We do not hang out in there. It's a
very
>> strict space for rest, right? Um, so all
our lights are off. We only have a red
light on at night. We have this
eight-month old baby. I found it's been
very helpful for him to uh get back into
sleep schedules because we we fly her
family's on the West Coast. So whenever
we fly and come back, his sleepru uh
structure gets a little bit messed up.
And I do find that him just being in the
dark um helps him to kind of chill out
and um get tired. So I think sleep
hygiene is super important. So the other
thing is blue light, right? Um, so
there's been a lot of uh interesting
research coming out about blue light and
how it's hijacking um your circadian
rhythm. So your body is not putting out
nighttime hormones. Um it's sapping your
dopamine. That's why a lot of people are
doom scrolling on Instagram because
they're they're searching for a dopamine
hit, but their dopamine is actively
being uh sapped by the the blue light in
the screen. So blue light blocking
glasses, I think, are helpful for a lot
of people. Um so and then hormones,
right? like uh a hormone your
testosterone can help people with sleep.
Now I I don't look at it as like oh take
testosterone it's going to help you
sleep but I do have a lot of patients
who report to me oh once they started
their sleep was better.
>> Um gut inflammation is going to impact
sleep because it's going to impact your
neurotransmitters. Um thyroid function
is going to impact your sleep. So you
know this was a very long-winded answer
to say sleep is incredibly complex.
there's a lot of moving parts and I try
to address the person as a whole and
usually that will result in at least
some improvement of sleep. There's still
people who like it's it's just very
difficult. Uh that's that's very much
the minority of people. I think most
people will respond to any one of those
things or combination of the things that
I mentioned.
>> Yeah. You mentioned growth hormone
peptides. Uh what's your opinion on GH
secrets? Do you use it just to optimize
uh growth hormone?
>> I do. I do. Uh so I like to use it so I
work with a lot of athletes. Uh so I
like to I love using it with BPC
um to uh improve their recovery from an
injury. Um recently I had seen an
article saying that the possible
mechanism of BPC uh improving injuries
was actually improving sensitivity to
growth hormone. Now, I don't think that
was proven. Uh, but we know growth
hormone can help with injury recovery.
We know BPC helps with injury recovery.
So, I think naturally they go together
very well. Uh, regardless of what the
mechanism is. Um,
so, you know, and then a lot of people
who are like, you know, I really don't
want to get on testosterone. I'm really
worried about my fertility, but I want
to improve my uh my my gym, like my uh
my gains, my stamina, my recovery. Um,
and I think they're great if they're
IGF-1 is low or sub-optimal. I think
they're really great candidates uh for
growth hormone peptides. Um, so yeah,
I'm I'm a big fan.
>> You talk about um ceremorulin,
tesamorin, things like that.
>> Yeah, I I curl is great. Obviously, it's
FDA approved. Um, so that one is uh
it's the least controversial, I guess we
could say. Tesla Morlin is also FDA
approved. Um, I have had a few patients
have some side effects from it. Nothing
nothing scary, but it's kind of made me
put it like, okay, let's try something
else first, and if that's not working
for you, then we can go to Tesla
Morland. But, I mean, it is the most
powerful. I find it gives the most boost
to the IGF-1. Um, and then it does have
the abdominal fat. Um, it it improves or
decreases your abdominal fat. So,
obviously, it's a very uh wanted
um effect for a lot of people, but it's
also the priciest of the of the growth
hormones of Greg Gogg. So, um I I kind
of like to discuss all of them and use
that as like a backup unless somebody's
like, "No, no, I really want that one."
Then, okay, fine. But I just want them
to be aware that I do find that there's
more side effects with that one. Do you
do you use peptides in your practice?
>> No. No. As a dermatologist, uh sometimes
people ask for melanotan, but I cannot
recommend that in good.
>> Sure.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Um it's it's interesting, you
know, and there's a lot of different um
there's different quality of peptides,
right? A lot of people are ordering
things online, which I would definitely
recommend not doing. Um you can't we
don't know about their sterility. We
don't know how much of the product
they're actually putting in there. Um,
we don't know how they're storing the
product.
Um, so I mean that's that's kind of a
big issue over here right now. But I
mean I use a compounding pharmacy so I
feel very comfortable with the peptides
that I I offer.
>> Yeah, sure. Um, do you also optimize
other hormones like DHEA and
pregnenolone?
>> Um, DHEA. Yes, definitely. I don't often
check pregnen alolone um because it's I
mean it's almost half the price of my
hormone panel alone um but I will I've
started to do so more recently
incorporating more pregnalone into my u
uh into my recommendations u dha
definitely I'm a big fan of DHEA
um
you know it's uh it has mood benefits
brain benefits it's anti-inflammatory
obviously it's a weaker version of
testosterone. So, it does have some
androgen effects. So, I really do like
to use DHEA.
>> Yeah. Awesome. Um yeah, I I I was told
by other doctors before that starting
from a certain age, maybe 40 45. So, for
men getting older, you should um yeah,
optimize all the hormones at once and
DHA and pregnnenolone and thyroid and
testosterone and so on. Um you have the
same opinion? Um, well, I'm I'm looking
at labs, right? So, if if something's
optimal, my goal is to start with
supplementation, you know, other than
testosterone, like with thyroid, um,
there's great supplements out there
that'll support your thyroid function.
Healing the gut will support your
thyroid function, but when you're on
TRT, you I do commonly see a decrease in
pregnenolone and DHEA. So, it's
definitely not a bad idea uh to monitor
and have people supplement with those as
well because if you're when you're on
testosterone, there is going to be at
least somewhat of a shutdown to the HBA
access and that is going to impact your
pregn and DHEA. So, in my opinion, it is
wise um to evaluate uh and take them if
you need to, which you probably will.
Mhm. Um, concerning fertility, if you
have relative young uh patients, maybe
30, 35 getting on TRT, uh, what do you
do for fertility or to maintain
fertility?
>> Yeah, great question. Um, so for some
people I start with incl.
Um, and then if they want to maintain
fertility while they're on TRT, then
they can do either ATCG or inclapene.
And I tell them like, our goal is to
just have everything operational. We're
not trying to get you to actively put
out testosterone. We just want your body
not to forget how to do so. Uh, so
that's really the goal. And um, so yeah,
definitely in younger men, I'm I'm
having conversations about this. I'm
always bringing up fertility. Even if
you're 99% sure you're never going to
have another kid, that's too much. We're
still I still want to put you on
something to maintain your fertility
because you have the right to change
your mind, right? Of course, just like
anybody does and we don't want a
decision you made five or 10 years ago
to be the reason that you can't have a
family in the future. So to me that's
always a high priority. Um you know some
a lot of guys are like I had a vasectomy
like I you don't need to worry about
this and okay fine then we definitely
don't need to worry. So then I don't
worry about it too much. But yeah, my
cuto off is like men under 50, we're
having a very much a conversation about
your fertility and where you stand on
that.
>> You you don't get all those men on ACG,
do you?
>> Um,
I don't force anybody uh because of
course there is a price component to
that. The more things you're adding uh
the more expensive uh your protocol is
going to be. Um, but it's it's very much
personto person. Um, and I want them to
know like if you want to make sure that
you are able to get off testosterone and
have kids again, you need to be on
something to help maintain fertility.
And uh, most I don't get too much
argument on that one. Most people are
just fine with it.
>> All right. All right. Okay. So, maybe to
round this up uh, let's get back uh to
to the gut. what we started with. I
asked myself, where do the endocrine
disrupting chemicals come in? Do they
enter the bloodstream more easily in
people with leaky gut? Is that the
reason?
>> Wow, that's a great question. Um, you
know, I I can't say I've looked into
that specifically, but if I had to
guess, I would say definitely. Um,
because, you know, the gut is actually
outside of the body, right? The area
between the mouth and the rectum is
outside of us. So we really want a
strong powerful barrier to keep things
out that shouldn't be. Now you know
endocrine disruptors also come in this
uh in the form of fragrances which is a
big one. So those are bypassing the GI
system entirely and getting into the
blood you know through the lungs. Um but
I would say anything that's an oral
endocrine disruptor will likely cause
more problems in somebody who has leaky
gut and definitely somebody who doesn't
eliminate properly. So, you know, I've
heard I've heard doctors say it's okay
to have a bowel movement once a week.
That is crazy to me. Like, no, it's not
okay to have a bowel movement once a
week. Like, you're you're recycling all
kinds of toxins. Everything that your
body is trying to get rid of, it's
either going through sweat, stool, or
urine. And and stool is going to be a
big one. So, we need healthy forms of
elimination. So, you know, if somebody
is having bowel movements once a week
and they haven't had like their T3
levels checked, they they're not taking
magnesium, you there's so much
lowhanging fruit to having normal bowel
function. That's very much not
non-invasive and just really just
nutrient uh repletion, not even, you
know, we're going extra and above and
beyond here. Um, increasing your fiber
intake. Um so all all of those things
are are super important. Elimination is
super important. Um so yeah in if you
are getting no endocrine disruptors but
you have healthy um elimination then
those are definitely going to be less of
a problem for you. So not only yes leaky
gut I would I would hypothesize it will
impact how much you're absorbing these
things and then also how poorly or how
efficiently you're eliminating is going
to further impact how well you're
absorbing these.
>> Yeah. Sure. Makes sense. Okay, Dr. Sean,
thank you so much uh for being on uh and
for sharing your knowledge. Anything
more you wanted um to add or advice to
the viewers? Um well, thank you so much
for having me. I really enjoyed having
this conversation with you. Um you know,
I would say it always comes back to
sleep, diet, exercise. Everything else
comes after those things. Um, obviously
get your hormones checked, get your labs
checked first. We need to know if
there's a problem to fix the problem,
right? Um, and I think too many people
wait uh too long, you know, the sooner
you go um the more data we have, right?
Like even if you're healthy, let's just
know what your normal is. You can do
labs once a year or once every two years
and you can start to trend. Oh,
something changed. My my testosterone
levels are starting to go down. What
habit has changed? what have I created
or what am I doing that's that's
impacting this. So, I think we're at a
point um where it's never been easier to
get this data. Um you know, it's it's
not super expensive and I think it's a
very worthwhile investment because if
your health is good, your focus is good,
your concentration is good, that's going
to pay dividends in all other aspects of
your life and it starts with your
health. So, data is is very helpful,
very important.
>> Great advice. Even myself as a doctor, I
only checked testosterone for the first
time when I was 42 and then it was 210
nanogs per deciliter. So I checked it
when I was symptomatic and low. So that
was too late. I've never known my
normal.
>> Yeah. And I mean and doctors uh we're
the worst. I find like doctors are don't
make good patients, but also our
lifestyles like you know uh I don't know
what training is like in Europe, but I'm
sure it's very rigorous and stressful
and you know the residency like there
was a study that showed it takes years
off of people's lives. Their DNA was
shortening. Our telomeres were
shortening during residency. So you know
our hormones take a hit, our
inflammation levels go crazy, our stress
hormone goes high. Um, you know, it's
it's tough, but you know, we do it
because we love it, right?
>> Yeah, sure thing. Okay, thank you so
much and talk to you next time.
>> All right, sounds good. Nice meeting.